<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The fall of man by sinne delivered in a sermon preached at the late solemne fast, Aug. 28, 1644 : wherein these three positions are briefly handled : 1. That all men are miserably fallen from God by sin, and are in a lost condition, 2. That we must see ourselves thus fallen, and utterly lost in ourselves, before we can convert and turn to God by repentance, 3. That formes of prayer may, in some cases be lawfully and warrantably used : published at the request of that truly religious and vertuous gentlewoman, mistris Elizabeth Barnham, wife to the worshipfull Robert Barnham, Esq. / by William Newport, Preacher of the word at Boughton Monchelsey in Kent.</title>
            <author>Newport, William, Preacher of the word at Boughton Monchelsey in Kent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53117</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N940</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3278</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12782608</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12782608</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93849</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53117)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93849)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 699:27)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The fall of man by sinne delivered in a sermon preached at the late solemne fast, Aug. 28, 1644 : wherein these three positions are briefly handled : 1. That all men are miserably fallen from God by sin, and are in a lost condition, 2. That we must see ourselves thus fallen, and utterly lost in ourselves, before we can convert and turn to God by repentance, 3. That formes of prayer may, in some cases be lawfully and warrantably used : published at the request of that truly religious and vertuous gentlewoman, mistris Elizabeth Barnham, wife to the worshipfull Robert Barnham, Esq. / by William Newport, Preacher of the word at Boughton Monchelsey in Kent.</title>
                  <author>Newport, William, Preacher of the word at Boughton Monchelsey in Kent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 27 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by L.N. for Richard Wodenoth ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sin --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93849:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93849:1"/>
            <p>THE FALL OF MAN BY SINNE. Delivered in a SERMON PREACHED AT THE LATE SOLEMNE Faſt, <hi>Aug.</hi> 28. 1644. WHEREIN THESE THREE Poſitions are briefly handled.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 That all men are miſerably fallen from God by ſin, and are in a loſt condition.</item>
               <item>2 That we muſt ſee our ſelves thus fallen, and utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lost in our ſelves, before we can convert and turne to God by repentance.</item>
               <item>3 That formes of Prayer may, in ſome caſes be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and warrantably uſed.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Publiſhed at the Requeſt of that truly reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious and vertuous Gentlewoman, Miſtris ELIZABETH BARNHAM, wife to the Worſhipfull ROBERT BARNHAM, <abbr>
                  <hi>Eſq</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>BY WILLIAM NEWPORT, Preacher of the Word at <hi>Boughton Monchelſey</hi> in <hi>Kent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Imprimatur. JOHN DOWNAME.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>L. N.</hi> for <hi>Richard Wodenoth,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the ſigne of the Starre in Corne-hill. 1644.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:93849:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:93849:2"/>
            <head>THE FALL OF MAN BY SINNE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>HOSE. 14.1, 2.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>1.</hi> O Iſrael returne unto the Lord thy God, thou haſt fallen by thine iniquity.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>2.</hi> Take with you words, and turne unto the Lord, ſay unto him take away all iniquity, and receive us gratiouſly.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the three firſt verſes of this Chapter, the Prophet exhorts the men of Iſrael to repentance: Firſt, Moving them to the duty, <hi>verſe</hi> 1. Secondly, Preſcribing them the manner how they ſhould performe it, <hi>verſe</hi> 2, 3. In the former we have, firſt the duty to be done, to turne to the Lord their God. Secondly, an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument to move them to it, taken from their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery in continuing in their ſinnes, <hi>Thou haſt fallen by thine iniquity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of the duty ſomething already. A few words
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:93849:3"/>now of the Argument to move them to it, taken from their miſery by ſin, <hi>Thou haſt fallen by thine iniquity;</hi> here is not a word that hath any diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty in it. The metaphor is taken from blind men that walke in rough places, that ſtumble and fall, to the breaking of their bones, yea, to the loſſe of their lives. The condition of theſe men is the condition of us all, wee have all ſtumbled by ſinne, and plunged our ſelves into a bottomleſſe gulfe of miſery and deſtruction. From hence we may conclude two things:</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. That all men are miſerably fallen from God by ſin, and are in a loſt condition.</item>
               <item>2. That we muſt ſee our ſelves thus fallen and utterly loſt, before we will convert and turne to God by repentance. For this cauſe the Prophet here ſhewes them their miſery in this regard, when he moves them to this maine duty.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Concerning the former, that wee are all fallen from God, and are in a loſt condition. There is a two-fold fall: Firſt, a corporall fall, ſuch was that of <hi>Mephiboſheth,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.4. and ſuch was <hi>Abners</hi> fall by the hand of <hi>Joab,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.38. Secondly, there is a ſpirituall and metaphorical fal, and ſuch was the fal of thoſe Iſraelites, and is the fal of us al as we are in nature. And this fal is either into ſin, <hi>A Biſhop must not be a novice, lest being lifted up with pride, hee fall into the condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the devill,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.6. that is, into that ſinne for which the devill was condemned. <hi>They that will be rich fall into temptation, and a ſnare,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:93849:3"/>and into many fooliſh and hurtfull luſts, which drowne men in deſtruction and perdition,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.9. Or elſe, ſecondly, into puniſhment and miſery, by reaſon of ſin. <hi>Prov.</hi> 24.16. <hi>A juſt man falleth ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven times, and riſeth againe, but the wicked ſhall fall into miſchiefe.</hi> Into both theſe we are all falne, both into ſin, and into miſery by reaſon of ſinne. Into ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.10. <hi>There is none righteous, no not one, there is none that underſtandeth or ſeeketh after God, they are all gone out of the way, they are toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther become unprofitable, there is none that doth good, no not one.</hi> Verſe 23. <hi>All have ſinned, and come ſhort of the glory of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as into ſin, ſo into miſery by reaſon of ſin; we are all falne, as <hi>we are all by nature dead in ſinne, ſo we are all children of wrath, Epheſ.</hi> 2.1, 3. <hi>The wages of ſinne is death, Rom.</hi> 6. <hi>ult.</hi> Of death there are three ſorts, ſpirituall, temporall and eternall; all theſe we have contracted by our fal into ſinne. And therefore this our fall is not like that of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiboſheth,</hi> who got onely a lameneſſe by his fall, nor like that of <hi>Eutichus,</hi> who though he fel from the third loft, yet had his life in him, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.10. but like the fal of <hi>Abner,</hi> who died in his fal, and like that of <hi>Jezebel,</hi> who being throwne out at a window had her braines in her fal daſhed out, and being ſought, for burial, had nothing found of her but her skull, and her feet, and the palmes of her hands, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 9.35.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By this fal we have contracted ſpiritual death, the death of our ſoules: <hi>And you being dead in your
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93849:4"/>ſinnes, and the uncircumciſion of your fleſh hath hee quickened, Coloſſ.</hi> 2.12. And it appeares that we are al thus ſpiritually dead, in that wee are al by nature deprived of al ſpiritual ſenſe. As firſt of ſpiritual ſight, <hi>Revel.</hi> 3.17. <hi>And knowe it not that thou art wretched, and miſerable, and poore, and blind.</hi> The condition of him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 9. is the con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of us al, wee are al borne blind, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. True 'tis, ſome notions of a deity and of right and wrong we have to maintaine humane ſociety and to leave without excuſe; but theſe are, as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive,<note place="margin">Onmes natura ſurdi &amp; coeci donec aures &amp; corda ſpiritu Dei aperiantur &amp; perforentur. Pareus in loc.</note> no reliques of Gods Image, but reimpreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, for by nature, <hi>the whole frame of mans heart is only evill, Gen.</hi> 6.5. Secondly, Of hearing, wee have no eares ſpiritually to heare, that is, ſo as to learne and obey, unleſſe God give them us, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.3. <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.9.13. <hi>Who hath eares to heare, let him heare: Loquitur de auribus cordis non cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris,</hi> He ſpeakes of the eares of the ſoule, not of the body. Thirdly, Of Reliſh, for wee have no more reliſh of divine things then hath a dead man of dainties, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.5. <hi>They that are after the fleſh, do ſavour</hi> or reliſh <hi>the things of the fleſh; and they that are after the ſpirit, the things of the ſpirit.</hi> We find no more ſavour in prayer, reading, Sermons, then <hi>reliſh in the white of an egge, Job</hi> 6.6. or then a dead man in his meat. Fourthly, Of Feeling, pricke a living man but with the leaſt pin and hee will ſtart, but potch a dead man with knives, ſtab him with daggers, or lay the waight of a moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine upon him, and hee feeles nothing; and ſo
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:93849:4"/>dead are we naturally in our ſinnes, that let them make never ſo deepe gaſhes in our ſoules, we feele them not; yea, though whole mountaines of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity lay on us, wee are not ſenſible of them, wee are by nature <hi>past feeling,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.19. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> have ſtone in our hearts, yea, our whole hearts of ſtone, and are not pained with them, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.26.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Dead men are deprived of the faculty of ſpeaking; ſo wee cannot ſpeake the language of <hi>Canaan, Iſa.</hi> 19.18. wee cannot ſpeake in a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual manner, either in prayer to God, or by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction or comfort to the edification of our brethren.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Dead men have no faculty locomotive, they move no further then moved; no more can wee move ſpiritually in the worke of God, we can do nothing that hath all the ingredients of a good worke in it. Moral workes may be done, and the carkas of ſpiritual ones may be produced, as wee may come to Church, heare after a ſort, and ſeeme to joyne in prayer, but all this without heart, ſpirit and life. Clockes and jackes move, but not from internall principles of life, but onely from externall movers, weights and ſprings; and ſo may we, when in nature, and therefore when our plummet is downe, when our outward incentive is removed, and wee have our ends, wee ſhall give over moving,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Seorſim a me. Bez.</note> 
               <hi>Without me, or ſevered from me</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>yee can do nothing, Joh.</hi> 15.5.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Dead carkaſſes rot and ſtincke, and ſo are loathſome to mens noſtrils; we naturally rot and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:93849:5"/>ſtinck in the grave of our ſinnes, ſo that wee are hatefull to the noſtrils of the Almighty; yea, our beſt workes are loathſome and abomination unto him, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.13, 15.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As by ſinne we have falne, ſo as to deprive our ſelves of ſpiritual life, and bring death on our ſoules, ſo by it wee deprive our ſelves of corporal life too, and make our ſelves lyable to bodily death, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12. <hi>By one mans diſobedience ſinne entered into the world, and death by ſinne, and ſo death paſſed upon all men, becauſe all have ſinned, Rom.</hi> 8.10. <hi>If Chriſt be in you, the body is dead be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of ſinne,</hi> that is, liable to death through ſin: Yea, this our fall makes us lyable to al theſe affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and miſeries that we endure, which are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ambles to, and pieces of this death, and are called death in ſome places <hi>Exod.</hi> 10.17. <hi>Take away from mee this death only</hi> (ſaith <hi>Pharaoh</hi>) concerning the plague of the Locuſts: And all the judgements of famine, ſword, peſtilence, conſumptions, and agues, are fruits of this our fall and ſinne, <hi>Lev.</hi> 26. <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.</p>
            <p n="3">3 By this our fall we have deprivid our ſelves of eternal life, and have made our ſelves lyable to everlaſting death and deſtruction, and this ſtands of two parts, the privative, and the poſitive, of the puniſhment of loſſe, and of the puniſhment of ſenſe.</p>
            <p>The privative part of it, or the puniſhment of loſſe, is the want of the beatificall viſion, and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py fruition of the glorious God-head for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93849:5"/>which is thought by Divines to be greater then that of ſenſe or feeling; becauſe this is the loſſe of an infinite good, whereas that is only the tollerance of a finite evil. If the want of <hi>Abſolons</hi> enjoyment of the ſociety of his earthly father for a time were ſo great a puniſhment, as to move him rather to deſire death then life on thoſe termes, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.32. What then is the want of the preſence of our heavenly Father for evermore. Chriſt ſhall ſay to all unregenerate ones at the laſt day, <hi>Depart from mee, I never knew you, Mat.</hi> 7.23. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.41. <hi>Depart from me yee curſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The poſitive part or puniſhment of ſenſe, are exquiſite torments both of body and ſoule, in all the faculties of the one, and members of the other. Which in Scripture are ſometimes called <hi>outer darkneſſe,</hi> ſometimes <hi>the worme that dieth not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 25.30.</note> and ſometimes <hi>the fire that ſhall never be quenched,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Marke 9.46.</note> and by many other ſuch fearfull names, as are enough to ſtrike terrour and amazement into the hearts of the moſt preſumptuous ſinners, if they had any ſenſe in them. What the miſerable condition of thoſe that ſuffer them, is, wee may partly ſee by the earneſt requeſt that the rich man in the place of theſe torments made to <hi>Abraham, And he cryed and ſaid, Father Abraham have mercy on me, and ſend Lazarus that he may dip the tip of his finger in water and coole my tongue, for I am tormented in this flame, Luk.</hi> 16.24. The tip of his finger, either to ſhew that the torments of hell do make the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſpeake fooliſhly, for elſe why not a pale-full,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:93849:6"/>aſwell as a drop, or elſe to ſhew that they would be glad of the leaſt mitigation of ther paine. Thus we ſee how we have falne to the loſſe of life ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, temporal, and eternall.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quest. </seg>
               </label> If inquiry be made how it comes to paſſe that we thus fal to our utter undoing without infinite mercy.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> I anſwer, that this our fal is cauſed by the fal of our firſt parents in eating the fruit of the forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den tree. Our ſinne and miſery ariſeth from their ſin both imputed and imparted.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Imputed, for <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> were common perſons, they ſuſtained the perſon of all their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, whiles they ſtood, we al ſtood with them, when they fel, we al fel with them. As <hi>Levi</hi> paid tythes to <hi>Melchizedec</hi> in <hi>Abraham</hi> being in his loynes, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 7.9, 10. So we al ſinned in <hi>Adam,</hi> being in his loynes. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.18, 19. <hi>Therefore as by the offence of one, judgement came upon all men to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation; even ſo by the righteouſneſſe of one, the free gift came upon all men to the juſtification of life. For as by one mans diſobedience many were made ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; ſo by the obedience of one many ſhall be made righteous.</hi> Chriſts righteouſneſſe and obedience is ours by imputation: therefore, ſo is <hi>Adams</hi> ſin and diſobedience. In this ſin was the confluence of all ſins. Firſt, Infidelity and unbeliefe. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, unthankfulneſſe for their happy eſtate. Thirdly, Idolatry, in deſiring to deifie themſelves, to make themſelves like God. Fourthly, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of God, and rebellion againſt him. Fifthly,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:93849:6"/>Murther, yea, Parricide, in killing themſelves and all their poſterity. <hi>Adam</hi> was <hi>Parricida an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tequam parens.</hi> Sixthly, Intemperance and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſſe, in that all the fruits beſides would not ſerve their turne, but they muſt needs have that for their luſt. Seventhly, Theft, in ſeazing on that, which was none of their owne, without the owners leave. Eighthly, there was an aſſent to the falſe teſtimony of the Devil. Ninthly, an ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious deſire of an higher dignity then God had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them, yea, of the glory that belonged only to himſelfe. And therefore they erre that thinke there was nothing but intemperance and pride in it. Now al theſe ſinnes of theirs folded up in one, are juſtly devolved upon us their poſterity, and imputed unto us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Imparted, and thus we came by that origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal filth that pollutes both ſoule and body, <hi>viz.</hi> by propagation from our firſt Parents, <hi>Behold I was ſhapen in iniquity, and in ſinne did my mother conceive mee, Pſal.</hi> 51.5. This original ſin the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle demonſtrates <hi>à poſteriori,</hi> from the death of thoſe children that never committed actual tranſgreſſion, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.14. <hi>Nevertheleſſe, death reigned even from Adam to Moſes, even over them that had not ſinned after the ſimilitude of Adam's tranſgreſsion:</hi> They dyed; therefore they ſinned, but they ſinned not actually, therefore they were guilty of original ſin. Looke, as ignoble and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prous parents beget none but ignoble and leprous children, and as of ſerpents can come nothing but
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:93849:7"/>ſerpents; ſo of polluted parents come onely pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted children, for <hi>who can bring a cleane thing out of an uncleane? not one, Job</hi> 14.4. And this originall filth is called ſometimes <hi>Luſt, Rom.</hi> 7.7. ſometimes <hi>the law in the members,</hi> verſ. 23. <hi>the body of ſinne,</hi> verſ. 24. and <hi>the old man, Epheſ.</hi> 4.22. And this is the ſourſe and fountaine of all our actuall ſins, and cauſe of all our fals. <hi>Let no man ſay when he is tempted, I am tempted of God, for God cannot be tempted with evill, neither tempteth he any man. But every man is tempted when he is drawne away of his owne luſt and entiſed. Then luſt when it hath concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved bringeth forth ſinne, and ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> when it is finiſhed, bringeth forth death, James</hi> 1.13, 14, 15. Many put their greateſt miſcarriages upon the devil; the devil owed them a ſhame, and now he hath payed them; when as the chiefe cauſe of all our fals lyes in our own hearts. The devill can but ſuggeſt and ſollicit, he cannot compell us to ſin; if he did not plow with our owne heifer, work on our own cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, he could do us no hurt. And ſo long as this ſeed of all iniquity remaines in mens hearts, they would commit ſin if there were no devill to tempt them to it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> This informes of two things:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Since we have falne, and ſo falne, as hath been ſhewed, by our ſins, this diſcovers to us our great miſery, by reaſon of ſinne and iniquity. We have falne by it to our undoing, to our deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> from God, from bliſſe to miſery; falne not only to the breaking of our bones with <hi>David,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:93849:7"/>but to the breaking of our necks with <hi>Iezebel;</hi> faln ſo as that wee have loſt life ſpiritual, life eternal by our fal, and are in a loſt, dead and undone con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition without infinite mercy. We have deprived our ſelves of all ability to ſerve our God, and have made our ſelves ſlaves to the devil. We have made our ſelves children of wrath, and fit for nothing but to fry in hell for all eternity. We have plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged our ſelves from the top of our felicity to the gulfe of endleſſe miſery. We think them unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py that fall from honor to contempt, from wealth to beggery; O how unhappy are wee that have falne by our ſins from God to the devil, from the higheſt bliſſe to the loweſt infelicity! And in this caſe we are not able to helpe our ſelves, nor to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire helpe, nor to ſee our ſelves to want helpe, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe God be pleaſed to give us eyes. Few men, though they are thus falne, and thus miſerable, wil be brought to believe it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This ſhewes againſt the patrons of Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will and univerſall grace, that man hath no power to ſee light when preſented to him, unleſſe God give him eyes; no power to believe in Chriſt and to embrace him, unleſſe God give him an heart, no power to do any ſpirituall work, unleſſe God give life, ſtrength and ability. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.18. <hi>I know that in me, that is, in my fleſh dwelleth no good thing.</hi> Hence <hi>David</hi> prayes for the opening of his eyes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.18. <hi>Lord open thou mine eyes, that I may ſee the wonders of thy Law.</hi> And Saint <hi>Paul</hi> deſires light from God in the behalfe of the Epheſians,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:93849:8"/>
               <hi>That the eyes of your underſtanding being enligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened, yee may know what is the hope of his calling, and what the riches of the glory of his inheritance in the Saints, Epheſ.</hi> 1.18. And ſo for the <hi>Coloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians,</hi> he prayes <hi>That they might be filled with the knowledge of Gods will in wiſedome and ſpirituall underſtanding, Coloſſ.</hi> 1.9. And he ſhewes us that the act of beleeving is Gods gift, <hi>To you it is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven not only to beleeve, but likewiſe to ſuffer for his ſake, Philip.</hi> 1.29. And that the will to any good is wrought in us by God himſelfe, <hi>'Tis God that workes in you to will and to doe of his good pleaſure, Philip.</hi> 3.13. Not that God doth force the will, for then 'twere no will, but that he doth ſweetly incline it, <hi>ex nolentibus volentes facit,</hi> of unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling hee makes us willing to repent, beleeve and obey. The will is free from coaction or impul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but not from ſervitude. Men in ſtate of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſinne freely, that is to ſay, they are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to it, and yet they ſin neceſſarily too, for they cannot doe any thing without ſin.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quest. </seg>
               </label> But is God juſt then in puniſhing men that ſin neceſſarily, ſo that they cannot avoid it?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> I do not ſay that men are neceſſitated to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit every particular ſin that they are guilty of, for from outward acts of ſinne and uncleanneſſe, men in ſtate of nature have power to abſtaine; but this is that which I affirme, that they can doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but either materially or formally 'tis a ſin, for they are out of Chriſt, and therefore muſt needs faile in every act, either in matter, manner,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:93849:8"/>or end. Neither can God be charged with inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice in puniſhing wicked men that ſin neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe they have voluntarily loſt their liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and drawn this neceſſity of ſinning upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. God made us free-men; wee made our ſelves ſlaves, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.29.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Since we are thus dangerouſly falne, we ſhould be exhorted to labour to riſe again by repentance, and by faith in Chriſts bloud. This is the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets inference here, <hi>O Iſrael returne to the Lord thy God, for thou haſt falne by thine iniquity.</hi> Since thou haſt falne from God by ſin, therefore returne to him againe by repentance. And this wee are moved to on the ſame ground by the Apoſtle, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.14. <hi>Awake thou that ſleepest, ſtand up from the dead, and Christ ſhall give thee light.</hi> And Chriſt himſelfe hath the ſame inference in his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to the Church of <hi>Epheſus, Remember from whence thou art falne, and repent, Revel.</hi> 2.5.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> But poſſibly you will ſay, What would you have dead men doe, if our fall be ſuch that wee have ſpiritually ſlaine our ſelves by it, how can wee raiſe our ſelves from this death to life by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> Though of your ſelves you cannot repent or beleeve, yet you can come to the Word which is the inſtrument to worke faith and repentance, to convert you from ſin to God; the Law of God is perfect converting the ſoule, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.7. The Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell preached is <hi>Gods mighty power to ſalvation,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:93849:9"/>Rom.</hi> 1.16. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was ſent to the Gentiles, <hi>To turne them from darkneſſe to light, from the power of Satan unto God, Act.</hi> 26.18. And therefore we ſhould ſettle our ſelves under the meanes, and bring tractable hearts with us, willing to be new formed, and new moulded by this Word.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We ſhould pray to Chriſt to enliven us by his Spirit, for al ſpiritual life comes from him. Hence he is called <hi>the life, Joh.</hi> 14.6. the life cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally, becauſe he breathes the breath of ſpiritual life into the ſoules of his at their regeneration, as he did natural life into <hi>Adam</hi> at his creation. <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily I ſay unto you the houre is comming and now is, when the dead ſhall heare the voice of the Sonne of God, and they that heare ſhall live. For as the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath life in himſelfe, ſo hath hee given to the Sonne to have life in himſelfe, Joh.</hi> 5.25, 26. That is to ſay, ſpiritual life to conveigh to his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. And the truth is, that there is nothing that can raiſe us thus dangerouſly falne, but the ſame power that raiſed Chriſt from the dead, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.19, 20. And therefore we muſt have recourſe to to him by prayer, intreating him that he wil ſhew his power in raiſing us thus falne. And though it bee true that unregenerate men cannot make a prayer that God ſhall accept as a good worke, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are bad and out of Chriſt, yet they may make ſuch a prayer as he wil in his mercy heare; <hi>For hee feedes the very young Ravens that call upon him, Pſal.</hi> 147.9.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:93849:9"/>
            <p>Thus of the former, I come now to the latter Poſition, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That men muſt ſee themſelves thus falne, and in a loſt and undone condition, before they wil turne to God by repentance. Hence it is that the Prophets generally ſhew men their ſinnes, and the danger of them, before they exhort men to that duty. Thus the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> ſhewed the Jewes firſt their deplorable ſtate by reaſon of their ſinnes, before hee exhorted them to purge themſelves from them. Hee told them that they were worſe then the Oxe or the Aſſe;<note place="margin">Eſay 1.3.</note> that they were like a man leprous from the crowne of the head to the ſole of the foot, that they were as cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt as <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah</hi> before hee exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them to clenſe themſelves by the teares of true repentance, <hi>verſ.</hi> 16. And the ſame Prophet would have thoſe that followed after righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that ſought the Lord, to looke firſt to the Rocke from whence they were hewen, and to the hole of the pit from whence they were digged, that they might ſee their original ſinne, the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and their actual tranſgreſſion,<note place="margin">Eſa. 51.1, 2, 3.</note> the ſtreames that iſſued from thence before he promiſes them any comfort and conſolation. And in another place calleth only thoſe that thriſt, that is to ſay, that are apprehenſive of their want and miſery by ſinne, <hi>To come unto the waters,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 55.1, 2.</note> &amp;c. And our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour cals none to him for eaſe but thoſe that feele their ſinne a burthen, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.28. Men
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:93849:10"/>muſt firſt apprehend themſelves ſicke, or at leaſt in danger, in regard of their health before, they will ſeeke to the Phyſitian; ſo men muſt firſt finde themſelves ſicke of ſinne before they will repaire to the Phyſician of their ſoules. <hi>The whole need not a Phyſician, but they that are ſicke. I came not to call the righteous, but ſinners to repentance, Matth.</hi> 9.12. That is to ſay, not thoſe that are puffed up with an opinion of their owne righteouſneſſe, as the Phariſees were, but thoſe that ſee their ſins, and ſee themſelves to be in great danger by reaſon of them, yea, utterly undone by them.</p>
            <p>The Reaſons are two, whereof the one reſpects ſinners to be converted; the other God, to whom they are to convert and turne.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> In regard of ſinners, ſuch is the pride of their nature, that they will not humble themſelves and ſeeke to him, untill they ſee themſelves in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame need of him, and utterly undone without his mercy, which they can never doe without a through ſight of the hainouſneſſe of their ſinnes. This we may ſee in the example of the Prodigall, whiles his portion laſted, nay, whiles he could any way ſubſiſt without his father, though it were by ſwines meat, he could be never brought to thinke of returning home, but when hee was denied the huskes of the ſwine; ſo that hee could by no meanes ſubſiſt without his father, then hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to returne home to him by weeping croſſe,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:93849:10"/>and to ſay, <hi>Father I have ſinned</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Luke</hi> 15.16, 17.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> In regard of God, for hee will have men thus loſt in their owne eſteeme, before grace bee ſhewed them in their converſion, and accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that they may learne to price him and his grace when they doe enjoy them: Wee can never know the worth of grace, unleſſe wee know the want of it. And hence wee ſee that CHRIST calleth none unto him, but them that finde their want of him: <hi>If any man thirſt let him come unto me and drinke, Joh.</hi> 7.37. <hi>And let him that is a thirst, come. And whoſoever will, let him take the water of life freely, Revel.</hi> 22.17.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> This ſhewes the duty of Miniſters in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, which is to teach men the great miſery they are in by reaſon of their ſins, that they are hereby the children of wrath, and liable to eternall death, that ſo they may turne to God for mercy, and to this end, to ſhew them the hainouſneſſe of their ſins, and the impoſſibility to be ſaved by the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of workes. Thus doth the Prophet here, <hi>Thou haſt fallen,</hi> &amp;c. And therefore <hi>Take unto you words, and turne to the Lord, and ſay unto him, Take away our iniquity, and receive us graciouſly.</hi> And ſo doth the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> he tels us againe and againe, that in the Law wee can ſee nothing but our ſins, and our wofull eſtate by reaſon of them: <hi>By the Law</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>comes the knowledge of ſinne;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 7.7.</note>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:93849:11"/>and he ſhewes that in the Law wee may reade our condemnation, written in ſuch faire characters, that he that runs may reade it. <hi>For</hi> (faith he) <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes deſcribeth the righteouſneſſe that is of the Law, that the man that doth thoſe things ſhall live in them, Rom.</hi> 10.5. and therefore he tels, us that <hi>the Law is our ſchoole-master to drive us unto Christ, Galath.</hi> 3.24. Without all queſtion it is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary that we ſhould ſee our ſin and danger by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of it, or elſe we ſhal never come to Chriſt for remiſſion and ſalvation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This ſhould teach every one that deſires to convert and turne to God by repentance, to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to ſee how farre he is falne from God by ſin, and in what miſery he is by reaſon hereof, and to this end he ſhould view his heart and life, not in the falſe glaſſe of his owne or others corrupt opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion or fancy, but in the looking-glaſſe of Gods Law that will not flatter him, that ſo hee may ſee the deformity and filth of the one, and the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities and wanderings of the other, and the juſt reward of both, <hi>viz.</hi> eternall wrath and deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Unleſſe we all thus doe (which Iſrael at the exhortation of the Prophet here) wee ſhall never turne to the Lord our God, wee ſhall never ſeeke him with earueſtneſſe, as men undone without it, for grace and mercy, <hi>If thou Lord ſhouldeſt bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame to marke iniquity, O Lord who ſhall ſtand, but there is mercy with thee, that thou mighteſt bee fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, Pſal.</hi> 130.3, 4. We muſt ſee our ſelves ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:93849:11"/>undone in rigour of juſtice, before we will appeale to the Throne of Mercy.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Verſ. 2, 3.</bibl>
               <p>Take with your words, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>HEre the Prophet ſhewes them the manner how hee would have them performe the duty, hee would not have them come to the Lord empty, but with theſe words, <hi>Take away all iniquity, and</hi> &amp;c. where he doth endevour to ſupport their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity, becauſe a mind aſtoniſhed knowes not what to ſay, for <hi>Curae leves loquuntur ingentes ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent;</hi> therefore he preſcribes them a ſhort, but a pithy forme, <hi>Turne to the Lord and ſay, Take away,</hi> &amp;c. Where wee have a kind of <hi>Antitheſis</hi> laid downe betweene true and falſe repentance, as if he ſhould have ſaid, Yee have hitherto ſought the Lord with ſheepe and oxen, chap. 5.6. yee have thought to pleaſe him with theſe ſacrifices, which hee loathes without true repentance. But now (ſaith he) <hi>Take unto you words,</hi> and ſhewes them what words they ſhould uſe. And leſt they ſhould thinke that there was nothing elſe but bare words required of them to be uttered like Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rots, without underſtanding, apprehenſion, or heart, as hypocrites doe, who thinke they have done enough when they have run over a forme of confeſſion and praiers, though after never ſo heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe a maner; he ſhews that the thing ſignified by theſe words likewiſe is neceſſarily required, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:93849:12"/>True converſion and turning to God, that the mouth in prayer may ſpeake from the heart, and the heart by the mouth; and therefore hee addes, <hi>Turne to the Lord and ſay, Take away all iniquity,</hi> &amp;c. (that is) ſay it not only with your mouthes, but from your hearts. And the forme of words preſcribed them ſtands of two parts: Firſt, of a petition for mercy: Secondly, a reſtipulation of duty; without the one we cannot be ſaved, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the other we ſhall ſhew our ſelves ungratefull hypocrites; and therefore both are neceſſary to true converſion. The benefits that hee teacheth them to aske of God are two: Firſt, That hee would remove all their evils of faults, guilt, and puniſhment; <hi>Take away all iniquity,</hi> and they ſay, <hi>All,</hi> becauſe they acknowledge themſelves guilty, not of one ſin, or of a few tranſgreſſions, but pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted with many: This is a petition for the remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſins. Secondly, They are taught to aske acceptation, regeneration by the Spirit, and the continuance of outward benefits in theſe words, <hi>Receive good,</hi> as 'tis in the originall, that is, take it, as it were, in thine hand to give it us: As <hi>Agar tooke a wife to Iſmael her ſonne,</hi> that is, gave him one:<note place="margin">Gen. 21.21.</note> And as Chriſt, when he aſcended up on high, <hi>received gifts for men, Pſal.</hi> 68.18. that is to ſay, to beſtow them upon them. The ſumme of the petition therefore, is, pardon our ſinnes, accept us in Chriſt, regenerate and guide us by thy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, remove our calamities, and afford us ſuch tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porals
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:93849:12"/>as are neceſſary for us. In the reſtipulation we have a double promiſe; 1. That they would ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrate the name of God with praiſe for his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aſhur</hi> ſhall not ſave, &amp;c.</note> ſo will we render the calves of our lips. 2. That they would reforme their lives, and ſo; Firſt, That they would renounce all their ſinnes, eſpecially their confidence in creatures and idols. Secondly, That they would endevour to performe their duties, eſpecially that which they had ſo much neglected, <hi>viz.</hi> that they would hence-forth depend upon their God, as a pupill or fatherleſſe child upon his guardian. So that in the manner of their repentance preſcribed: we have,</p>
            <p>Firſt, the preſcription of a forme of Prayer, <hi>Take with you words, returne, and ſay.</hi> Secondly, the ſubſtance of the forme preſcribed, which ſtands; Firſt, of a Petition: Secondly, Reſtipu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. The Petition ſtands, Firſt, of depreca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the removall of evill, <hi>Take away all</hi> &amp;c. Secondly, Supplication for acceptation, and a ſupply with all benefits ſpirituall and temporall. In the Reſtipulation they promiſe, Firſt, praiſe for mercies: Secondly, amendment of life. Firſt, that they would abjure and renounce their former evil courſes: Secondly, that they would performe neglected duties.</p>
            <p>I begin with his preſcription of a forme. In that to helpe their weakneſſe, he preſcribes them one; wee may learne, That formes of prayer in ſome caſes may lawfully and warrantably be uſed. As the people here by our Prophet, ſo the Prieſts by the Prophet <hi>Joel</hi> are preſcribed a forme; <hi>Let
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:93849:13"/>the Prieſts, the Miniſters of the Lord weepe between the Porch and the Altar, and ſay, Spare thy people,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Joel</hi> 2.17. <hi>Moſes,</hi> a Prophet of the Lord, who talked with him face to face, uſed one forme when the Arke ſet forward, and another when it reſted; <hi>Ariſe, O Lord, and let thine enemies bee ſcattered, and let all that hate thee flee before thee. And return, O Lerd, to the many thouſands of Iſrael, Numb.</hi> 10.35, 36. And ſo the Prieſt uſed a forme of prayer to bleſſe the people withall, <hi>Numb.</hi> 6.23, 24. <hi>The Lord bleſſe thee and keepe thee,</hi> &amp;c. The <hi>Pſalmes</hi> are ſome of them wholly prayers, and ſome prayers for the moſt part, and yet all uſed by the Jewes in the ſolemne worſhip of God, in the formes wherein they are written. Our Saviour taught his Diſciples a forme, ſaying in one place, <hi>After this manner, Matth.</hi> 6.9. and in another, <hi>When yee pray, ſay, Luke</hi> 11.2. intimating thereby that it may be uſed as a prayer, ſo that it be done with underſtanding and heart, and not uſed onely as a copy to write by. Laſtly, the Apoſtle uſeth formes of benediction and malediction, <hi>Grace to you and peace,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c. And ſince hee uſed ſhort formes, no doubt, but we in ſome caſes may uſe long ones.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quest. </seg>
               </label> But in what caſes may we uſe them?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> In caſe of infirmity, as here, when Chriſtians for lack of naturall abilities, of invention, memory, orutterance, or being newly converted, for want of exerciſe in the Word of life, and for want of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience are not able to expreſſe themſelves with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a forme; there is no doubt but they may make
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:93849:13"/>uſe of a forme either written, or printed, or learnt by heart. As a man that is lame may make uſe of his crutches, or a ſtaffe to helpe him to go; ſo may he that is weake in knowledge and utterance, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the time of his weakneſſe, make uſe of a forme to pray by. Howbeit, when it pleaſeth God to give him more ſtrength,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Perkins</hi> Caſes.</note> no doubt he is to lay aſide his formes (as a lame man recovered his crut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches) and to pray without them. For without queſtion every man is to ſerve God with his beſt abilities.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In caſe a man hath occaſion to aske againe and againe, or daily, the ſame things, there is no queſtion but a man may aske them in the ſame words, (therefore) a man daily needs pardon of ſinne, ſtrength of faith, fortitude and patience, &amp;c. There is no doubt but a man may aske theſe things daily in the ſame words; to aske the ſame things in variety of words every time, doth but ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue a quick apprehenſion, and nimble expreſſion; &amp;c. no doubt but he that askes them the ſame may aske them with as much earneſtneſſe and as good an affection as the other. Our Saviour in his ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſaid, <hi>Father if it be poſsible</hi> &amp;c. and went again and again, <hi>and uſed the ſame words, Matth.</hi> 26.49. Not that he that was the eternal Word of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wanted variety of words to expreſſe himſelf, but for our example, to ſhew that wee may even with zeale and earneſtneſſe aske the ſame things again and again in the ſame words. Howbeit, for a Chriſtian to be abſolutely word-bound, to be tied ſo to anothers forme or his own, that he hath no li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:93849:14"/>to vary in any expreſſion, is a great bondage and deading to his ſpirit, and may occaſion a great deale of meere formality in prayer.</p>
            <p>But now when a Chriſtian hath need to aske ſome ſpeciall mercy either in his own behalfe, or the behalfe of his neighbour, or in the behalfe of the whole Church of God, or when he receives ſome new mercy? There is no queſtion but he is to aske the one, and to give thankes for the other in new expreſſions. This therefore is that which I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine, <hi>viz.</hi> that weak Chriſtians may uſe forms as helps to their infirmity, until they gather more ſtrength, and that then they are to lay them aſide as a lame man his crutches when hee is recovered his lameneſſe. And as for thoſe that are better a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, they may aske thoſe things they daily need in the ſame words, and give thankes for thoſe things they daily receive in the ſame expreſſions, ſo that they looke that they bee not meerely formall in what they do; and that otherwiſe every growne Chriſtian is to vary as his occaſions do vary.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Harris</hi> in his <hi>Quaeries</hi> and caſes touching theory and practice of Prayer.</note> And this is the ſentence of one of our Divines of that Aſſembly, that comes behind none of them, as I ſuppoſe, for learning, naturall abilities, or grace.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> This blames therefore two ſorts of men:</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Anabaptiſts, and thoſe of the Sepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that condemne not only corrupt formes, but all formes of prayer, holding the uſe of them to be a meere ſuperſtitious will-worſhip; for they ſay it is not to pray in the ſpirit, and if the formes bee compoſed by others, that it is to worſhip God by mens inventions. Of whom I would know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:93849:14"/>the godly Jewes uſing this forme preſcribed by the Prophet with a good heart, did pray in the ſpirit or no? I hope they will not deny it. Next I would know by whoſe invention they worſhip God, when they conceive a prayer? If they ſhall ſay that 'tis by the invention of the Spirit of God; that is the opinion of the Entheuſiaſts, which look to have the Spirit put words into their mouthes, which is as much as ever it did for the Prophets and Apoſtles; whereas the Spirit in ordinary times, ſuch as ours only, ſtirs up holy deſires in the ſoule, the formation of theſe deſires into ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ball petitions depends upon mens naturall abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as we may ſee by every dayes experience, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2. The ſpirit helpeth our infirmities with ſighs and grones, not with words and phraſes. There are that looke for all thoſe gifts now, that the emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenteſt in the Apoſtles times had, <hi>viz. That their ſonnes and their daughters ſhall propheſie, that their old men ſhall dreame dreames, and that their young men ſhall ſee viſions, Joel</hi> 2.28. I am confident that many both old and young in this age dreame more dreames, and divulge them too, then tend to the glory of God, or the good of his Church. But why doe not theſe and their children undertake to foretell things to come too, as <hi>Agabus</hi> and others did in the Apoſtles times? If they cannot do that, Ile ne're beleeve they can ſpeak by the ſpirit of propheſie. Beſides, what do theſe men think of all thoſe formes of prayer mentioned before, uſed by <hi>Moſes,</hi> Chriſt and his Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> Reading and praying bee two things,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:93849:15"/>therefore a man cannot doe both at once, reade a forme and pray too.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> I deny the conſequence, they are two ſuch things as may well enough goe together. A man may ſing and pray, and therefore no doubt he may reade and pray too. The modulation of the voice in ſinging is as likely to take off the heart from the matter, as the uſe of the eye in reading.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Some formaliſts thinke that nothing can be done without formes, and therefore when they are in any diſtreſſe preſently they mumble over the Lords Prayer, or ſome other that they have learnt by rote, without any underſtanding or heart at all. Theſe are juſt like our fooliſh Papiſts that uſe their prayers in all temptations and afflictions as charmes and ſpels to remove the evils from them. This is only to take the Lords Name in vain, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe his Titles and his Word, and to provoke him to more wrath and indignation againſt them. Though I like not the former, yet I like theſe, you muſt thinke, worſe by many degrees; the former have ſome good-wil to Religion, though miſ-led; but theſe are groſſely ignorant, and dangerouſly hypocriticall, for they draw neere to God with their lips, and honour him with their mouthes, when their hearts are not with him.</p>
            <p>Let mee exhort thoſe that in regard of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and utterance cannot pray without the help of a forme, to labour to get good and wholeſome formes, and to make uſe of them; we ſee that the uſe of them in this caſe is warranted. But let ſuch take theſe two cautions along with them:</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:93849:15"/>
            <p n="1">1. Let them look that they be not meerly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall in what they do in this kind. And therefore they ſhould get them ſuch formes as they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, and muſt when they have them, looke that they utter them with an apprehenſion and feeling of their own wants in every petition, and with an earneſt deſire to have them ſupplyed, 'tis the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and the fervent prayer that prevailes with God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.15, 16. <hi>James</hi> 5.16.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let them not reſt upon forms, thinking they doe enough, becauſe they make uſe of them, and pray by them, but let them reſolve to uſe them on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as helpes to their dulneſſe and incapacity for a time, with a purpoſe to lay them aſide, when they ſhall through Gods grace and their earneſt ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours get more knowledge and better abilities. And therefore they, yea, all of us, ſhould be much imployed in ſearching out our own wants, and in the ſtudy of the holy Scriptures, that in the one wee may find matter of Prayer, and in the other we find out fit words and phraſes to expreſſe our ſelves in that variety of occaſions that wee ſhall meet withall, in the many turnings and windings of our lives. He that takes this courſe, with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution through Gods aſſiſtance to get ability in this kind, will find a great deale of comfort in it, and get that ability to ſpeak in prayer, <hi>pro re nata,</hi> as doth almoſt as much excell formes, as a living man doth a dead cakaſſe.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
